<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Articles to be enquired in the visitation, in the firste yeere of the raigne of our moste dread Soueraigne Lady Elizabeth, by the grace of God, of Englande, Fraunce, and Irelande, Queene, defendour of the faith. [and]c Anno domini. 1559.</title>
            <title>Visitation articles. 1559</title>
            <author>Church of England.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1577</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 16 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00132</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 10126</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S112404</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99847658</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99847658</idno>
            <idno type="VID">12710</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A00132)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 12710)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 459:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Articles to be enquired in the visitation, in the firste yeere of the raigne of our moste dread Soueraigne Lady Elizabeth, by the grace of God, of Englande, Fraunce, and Irelande, Queene, defendour of the faith. [and]c Anno domini. 1559.</title>
                  <title>Visitation articles. 1559</title>
                  <author>Church of England.</author>
                  <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1558-1603 : Elizabeth I)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Christopher Barkar, printer the Queenes Maiestie. Cum priuilegio regiæ maiestatis,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1577?]]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon; publication date suggested by STC.</note>
                  <note>In title: "firste yeere"--STC.</note>
                  <note>Last leaf blank.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Visitations, Ecclesiastical --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:12710:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12710:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>illustrated border framing title page</figDesc>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>Matthew the evangelist, represented by a winged man or an angel</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <q xml:lang="frm">HONI SOIT QVI MAL Y PENSE</q>
                     <figDesc>royal blazon surmounted by a crown</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>John the evangelist, represented by an eagle with outspread wings, holding a pencase and inkwell in its beak</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>emblematic representation of Faith with a flaming sword and shield</figDesc>
                     <head>FIDES</head>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>emblematic representation of Humility holding a lamb</figDesc>
                     <head>HVMILITAS</head>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>Mark the evangelist, represented by a lion</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>Luke the evangelist, represented by an ox</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <p>
                     <hi>ARTICLES to be enquired in the</hi> viſitation, in the firſte yeere of the raigne of our moſte dread Soueraigne La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Elizabeth, by the grace of God, of England, Fraunce, and Irelande, Queene, defendour of the Faith. &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>Anno domini. 1559.</p>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="articles_of_visitation">
            <pb facs="tcp:12710:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12710:2"/>
            <head>Articles.</head>
            <p>
               <label>1 Reſidencie.</label> 
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Irſt, whether anye Parſon, Vicar or Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat be reſident continually vp on his benefice doing his du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye in Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, reading and duely mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtring the ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes.</p>
            <p>
               <label>2 Falſe myra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles.</label> Item whether in their Churches &amp; Chappels, al images, ſhrines, all tables, candleſtickes trin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delles. and rolles of waxe, pictures, paintinges, and all other monumentes of faigned and falſe myracles, pilgrimages, Idolatrie, and ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, be remoued, aboliſhed, and deſtroyed.</p>
            <p>
               <label>3 The Lordes prayer.</label> Item, whether they doe not euery holy daye when they haue no Sermon, immediatelye after the Goſpell, openly, plainely and deſtinctlye, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite to their pariſhioners in the pulpit, the Lords prayer, the beleefe, and the ten commaundemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes in Engliſh.</p>
            <p>
               <label>4 To bring vp youth.</label> Item, whether they doe charge Fathers and mothers, maiſters, and gouerners of youth, to bring them vp in ſome vertuous ſtudie and occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:12710:3"/>
               <label>5 Curates.</label> Item whether ſuche beneficed men, as be lawfully abſent from their benefices, doe leaue their cures to a rude and vnlearned perſon, and not to an honeſt, wel learned, and expert Curat, which can and will teache you wholeſome doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine.</p>
            <p>
               <label>6 Reading the ſcripture.</label> Item, whether they do diſcourage any perſon from reading of any part of the Byble, eyther in Latine or Engliſhe, and doe not rather comforte and exhort euery perſon to reade the ſame at con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uenient times, as the very lyuely worde of God, and the ſpeciall foode of mans ſoule.</p>
            <p>
               <label>7 Tauernes and gaines.</label> Item whether Parſons, Vicars, Curates, and other miniſters, be common haunters and reſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters to Tauernes or Alehouſes, geuing them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to drinking, ryoting, and playing at vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull games, and doe not occupie themſelues in the reading or hearing of ſome parte of holye ſcripture, or in ſome other Godly excerciſe.</p>
            <p>
               <label>8 Preachers.</label> Item, whether they haue admitted any man to preache in their cures, not being lawfully li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſed thervnto, or haue bene licenſed according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye.</p>
            <p>
               <label>9 Superſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</label> Item, whether they vſe to declare to their pariſhioners, anye thing to the extolling or ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting foorth of vaine and ſuperſtitious religion, pilgrimages, reliques, or images, or lighting of
<pb facs="tcp:12710:3"/>candels, kiſſing, kneeling, or decking of the ſame images.</p>
            <p>
               <label>10 Regiſter.</label> Item, whether they haue one booke or regiſter kept, wherein they write the daye of euerye wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, chriſtning and burying.</p>
            <p>
               <label>11 Obedience</label> Item, whether they haue exhorted the people to obedience to the Queenes Maieſtie, and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, and to charity and loue one to another.</p>
            <p>
               <label>12 The Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</label> Item, whether they haue admoniſhed their pariſhioners, that they ought not to preſume to receiue the Sacrament of the bodye and blood of Chriſt, before they can ſay perfectly the Lordes prayer, the articles of the faith, and the ten com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundementes in Engliſhe.</p>
            <p>
               <label>13 Hoſpitalitie.</label> Item, whether they be reſident vpon their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefices, &amp; keepe hoſpitalitie or no. And if they bee abſent, and keepe no hoſpitalitie, whether they do relieue their pariſhioners, &amp; what they giue them.</p>
            <p>
               <label>14 Reparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</label> Item, whether Proprietaries, Parſons, Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cars, and Clarkes, hauing Churches, Chappels, and Manſions, doe keepe their Chauncels, Rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories, Vicarages, and al other houſes appertay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to them in due reparations.</p>
            <p>
               <label>15 Prayer in Engliſhe.</label> Item, whether they doe counſayle or moue their pariſhioners, rather to pray in a tongue not kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen, then in Engliſhe, or put their truſt in anye
<pb facs="tcp:12710:4"/>certaine number of prayers, as in laying ouer a number of Beades,<note place="margin">Beades.</note> or other like.</p>
            <p>
               <label>16 Diffamed perſons.</label> Item, whether they haue receiued anye per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to the Communion, being openlye knowne to be out of charitie with their neighboures, or diffamed with any notorious crime, and not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fourmed.</p>
            <p>
               <label>17 Pore mens boxe.</label> Item, whether they haue prouided, and haue a ſtrong cheſt for the poore mens Boxe, and ſet and faſtned the ſame in a place of the Churche, moſt conuenient.</p>
            <p>
               <label>18 Teſtament.</label> Item, whether they haue dilligently called vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, exhorted and mooued their pariſhioners, and eſpecially when they make their teſtamentes to geue to the ſayde pore mens boxe, and to beſtowe that vppon the poore, which they were wonte to beſtowe vpon pilgrimages, pardons, trentalles and vpon other like blinde deuotions.</p>
            <p>
               <label>19 Sick. Buriall.</label> Item, whether they haue denyed to viſite the ſycke, or burie the dead being brought to the Churche.</p>
            <p>
               <label>20 Simonie.</label> Item, whether they haue bought their Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefices, or come to them by fraude, guyle, deceit, or ſimonie.</p>
            <p>
               <label>21 Adulterers.</label> Item, whether they haue giuen open moni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to their pariſhioners, to detecte and preſent
<pb facs="tcp:12710:4"/>to their Ordinary all adulterers &amp; fornicatours, and ſuch men as haue two wiues liuing with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in their pariſhes.</p>
            <p>
               <label>22 Church goods.</label> Item, whether they haue moniſhed their pari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhioners openly, that they ſhould not ſell, geue, nor otherwiſe alienate, anye of their Churche goods.</p>
            <p>
               <label>23 Many bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices.</label> Item, whether they, or anye of them doe keepe mo benefices and other Eccleſiaſticall promoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons then they ought to doe, not hauing ſufficient licenſes, and diſpenſations therevnto, and howe many they be, and their names,</p>
            <p>
               <label>24. Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</label> Item, whether they miniſter the holye Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion any otherwiſe, then onelye after ſuche fourme and maner, as it is ſet foorth by the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon authoritie of the Queenes Maieſtie and the Parliament.</p>
            <p>
               <label>25 Letters of the word or preaching.</label> Item, whether you know any perſon within your parriſhe or elſe where, that is a letter of the worde of God to be read in Engliſhe, or ſincerely preached in place and times conuenient.</p>
            <p>
               <label>26 Goersout of the Church.</label> Item, whether in the time of the Letanye, or any other common prayer, in the tyme of the Sermon or Homilie, and when the Prieſt rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the ſcriptures to the pariſhioners, anye perſon haue departed out of the Churche with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out iuſt and neceſſarye cauſe, or diſturbe the
<pb facs="tcp:12710:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>Miniſter otherwiſe.</p>
            <p>
               <label>27 Churche money.</label> Item, whether the money comming and ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of any cattell, or other moueable ſtockes of the Churche, and money giuen and bequeathed to the finding of Torches, Lightes, Tapers, or Lampes, not payde out of any landes haue not bene employed to the poore mens cheſt.</p>
            <p>
               <label>28 Keepers of the Churche money.</label> Item, who hath the ſayde ſtockes and money in their handes, and what be their names.</p>
            <p>
               <label>29 Contempt of Prieſtes.</label> Item, whether any vndiſcreete perſon do vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charitably contemne &amp; abuſe Prieſtes and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of the Church.</p>
            <p>
               <label>30 The kinges Grammer.</label> Item, whether there be any other Grammer taught in any ſchoole within this Dioceſſe, then that which is ſet foorth by the aucthoritie of king Henry the eyght.</p>
            <p>
               <label>31 The time of Seruice.</label> Item, whether the ſeruice of the church be done at due and conuenient howers.</p>
            <p>
               <label>32 Talkers in the Church.</label> Item, whether any haue vſed to commune, iangle, and talke in the churche in the time of the prayer, reading of the Homilie, preaching, rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding or declaring of the ſcripture.</p>
            <p>
               <label>33 Hereſies.</label> Item, whether any haue wilfullye mayntay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and defended any hereſies, errours, or falſe opinions, contrary to the faith of Chriſt and holy ſcripture.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:12710:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <label>34 Drunkards.</label> Item, whether any be common drunkardes, ſwearers or blaſphemers of the name of God.</p>
            <p>
               <label>35 Adulterers.</label> Item, whether any haue committed adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, fornication or inceſt, or bee common bawdes, or receiuers of ſuch euill perſons, are vehemently ſuſpected of any of the premiſſes.</p>
            <p>
               <label>36 Brawlers.</label> Item, whether any be brawlers, ſlaunderers, chyders, ſcholders, &amp; ſowers of diſcord betweene one perſon and an other.</p>
            <p>
               <label>37 Sorcerers.</label> Item, whether you knowe anye that doe vſe charmes, ſorceries, inchauntmentes, inuocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, circles, witchcrafts, ſoothſaying, or any lyke craftes or imaginations inuented by the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, and ſpecially in the tyme of womens tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uayle.</p>
            <p>
               <label>38 Pulpittes.</label> Item, whether the Churches, Pulpittes, and other neceſſaries appertaining to the ſame, be ſufficiently repayred, and if they be not, in whoſe default the ſame is.</p>
            <p>
               <label>39 Reſorters to other Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches.</label> Item, whether you know any, that in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of their owne pariſhe Church doe reſorte to any other churche.</p>
            <p>
               <label>40 Inholders.</label> Item, whether any Inholders, or Alehouſe kepers, do vſe commonly to ſell meate and drinke in the time of common praier, preaching, reading of the Homilies, or ſcripture.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:12710:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <label>41 Deuorſe.</label> Item, whether you know any to bee maried within the degrees prohibited by the Lawes of God, or that be ſeparated or diuorſed withoute the degrees prohibited by the law of God, and whether any ſuch haue maried againe.</p>
            <p>
               <label>42 Priuie con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractes.</label> Item, whether you knowe any to haue made priuie contractes of matrimonie, not calling two or moe witneſſes therevnto, nor hauing thereto the conſent of their parents.</p>
            <p>
               <label>43 Banes.</label> Item, whether they haue maryed ſolemnelye, the banes not firſt lawfully aſked,</p>
            <p>
               <label>44 Executours.</label> Item, whether you knowe anye executors, or adminiſtratours of dead mens goodes whiche doe not only beſtowe ſuche of the ſayde goodes, as were giuen and bequeathed, or appointed to be diſtributed among the poore people repayring of high wayes, finding of poore ſchollers, or mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying of poore maydens, or ſuch other like chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table deedes.</p>
            <p>
               <label>45 Images.</label> Item whether you know any that keepe in their houſes any vndefaced Images, Tables Pictures, paintinges, or other Monumentes of faigned and falſe myracles, pilgrimages, ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrie and ſuperſtition, and do adore them, and ſpecially ſuche as haue bene ſet vp in Churches Chappels and Oratories.</p>
            <p>
               <label>46 <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ookes.</label> Item, what bookes of holye Scripture you
<pb facs="tcp:12710:6"/>haue deliuered to be burnt, or otherwiſe deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and to whome ye haue deliuered the ſame.</p>
            <p>
               <label>47 Bribes.</label> Item, what bribes the accuſers, promoters, perſecuters, Eccleſiaſtical Iudges, and other the Commiſſioners appointed within the ſeuerall Dioceſſe of this Realme, haue receiued by them ſelues or other of thoſe perſons whiche were in trouble, apprehended or impriſoned for Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p>
               <label>48 Loſſe of goods.</label> Item, what goods moueable, lands, fees, of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, or promotions, hath ben wrongfully taken awaye in the time of Queene Maries raigne, from anye perſon whiche fauoured the Religion now ſet foorth.</p>
            <p>
               <label>49 How many burnt.</label> Item, how many perſons for religion haue died by fyre, famine, or otherwiſe, or haue ben im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoned for the ſame.</p>
            <p>
               <label>50 Certificat of the dead.</label> Item, that you make a true preſentment of the number of all the perſons whiche dyed within your pariſhes, ſithen the feaſt of ſainte Iohn the Baptiſt, which was in the yeere of our Lord God a thouſand fiue hundred, fiftie and eyght, vnto the ſame feaſt laſt paſt, making therein a playne diſtinct declaration, howe manye men, women, and men children the ſame were, and the names of the men.</p>
            <p>
               <label>51 Secrete Maſſes.</label> Item, whether you knowe anye man in your
<pb facs="tcp:12710:7"/>pariſhe, ſecretely, or in vnlawfull conuenticles, ſay, or heare Maſſe, or any other ſeruice prohibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the law.</p>
            <p>
               <label>52 Falſe ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors. Unlawfull bookes.</label> Item, whether you knowe any perſon in your pariſh, to be a ſlaunderer of his neighbours, or a ſower of diſcord betwene partie and partie, man and wife, parentes &amp; their children, or that hath inuented, bruted, or ſet fourth any rumours, falſe and ſeditious tales, ſlaunders, or makers, brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, byers, ſellers, kepers, or conueighers of any vnlawful bokes which might ſtirre and prouoke ſedition, or maintaine ſuperſtitious ſeruice with in this realme, or any ayders, counſailers, procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers or maintainers therevnto.</p>
            <p>
               <label>53 Patrone. Tithes. Vacation.</label> Item, whether the Churche of your pariſh be now vacant or no, who is the patrone thereof, how long it hath bene vacant, who doeth receiue the tithes oblations, and other commodities, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the time of the vacation, and by what auc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, and in what eſtate the ſaide Churche is, at this time, and how long the Parſon or Vicar hath had that benefice.</p>
            <p>
               <label>54 Minſtrelles</label> Item whether any Minſtrelles, or any other perſons, doe vſe to ſing or ſay any ſonges, or Dit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties that be vile or vncleane, and ſpecially in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſion of any godly order now ſet foorth and eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed.</p>
            <p>
               <label>55 Letanie in Engliſh.</label> Item whether the Letany in Engliſhe with
<pb facs="tcp:12710:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>the Epiſtle &amp; Goſpel which was by the Queenes highneſſe proclamation willed to be read to the people, were put in vſe in your Churches, and if not, who were the letters thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <label>56 Diſtinct reading.</label> Item, whether the Curates and Miniſters do leiſurely, playnely, and diſtinctly reade the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique prayers, Chapters and Homilies, as they ought to doe.</p>
            <closer>God ſaue the Queene.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>JMPRINTED AT</hi> London, by Chriſtopher Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kar, <hi>Printer to the Queenes</hi> Maieſtie.</p>
            <p>Cum priuilegio Regiae Maieſtatis.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:12710:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12710:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12710:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12710:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
